A Guide to the Papers of the Institute of Public Affairs, University of Virginia, 1927-1953
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the Institute of Public Affairs, University of Virginia 1927-1953
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
RG-2/4/1.891, RG-2/4/1.892
148 boxes.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was transferred to University Archives on March 3, 1989.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Institute of Public Affairs at the University of Virginia was founded in 1927 by University President Edwin A. Alderman and Professor Charles G. Maphis. Prof. Maphis served as director of the Institute until his death in 1938. Successive directors were Professors Robert K. Gooch (1938), Hardy C. Dillard (1939-1941), Oron J. Hale (1942), and George B. Zehmer (1950-1953). The meetings of the Institute were organized with the cooperation and participation of President Alderman and his first two successors as University President, John L. Newcomb and Colgate W. Darden. According to its Statement of Purpose, "The Institute of Public Affairs [was] designed to advance the popular understanding of current public questions. [It] propose[d] to emphasize particularly the domestic problems of the United States and to have them discussed in a broad and competent fashion by men charged with the task of public administration and by those who are actively engaged in public affairs." The Institute of Public Affairs was modeled on the Institute of Politics at Williams College in Williamstown, Massachusetts, which dealt primarily with international issues. To avoid conflict, the Institute of Public Affairs confined itself to local, state, regional, and national issues until after the Institute of Politics was discontinued, whereupon the Institute began to employ discussions of foreign affairs. The Institute initially convened each summer for two weeks, usually between the months of June and July. Later, the length of the program was shortened to one week. The Institute met annually from 1927 until 1942, when it was temporarily discontinued due to the exigencies of the war. It was reconvened in 1950, and continued to meet annually until it was discontinued after the twentieth meeting in 1953.
Extraordinarily timely and unique in its style and format, the Institute hosted some of the most prominent statesmen in the nation and the world. The meetings of the Institute were originally organized into Morning Addresses, Afternoon Panel Discussions, and Evening Addresses. A "Round Table" format was used to organize the morning and afternoon sessions into particular themes which were spread out across the course of the Institute. After the death of Professor Maphis, the format was modified into Morning Addresses, Afternoon Addresses, and Evening Addresses, with a specific theme for each of the Morning and Afternoon sessions. Evening addresses became less-structured in order to cater to the tastes and interests of the speakers.
Scope and Content
This collection consists chiefly of correspondence, proceedings, manuscripts of speeches, registration cards, news letters manuscripts, and clippings. Correspondents include: Everett Ross Clinchy, Fred Essery, Frank Fuller, Henry (Harry) Augustus Garfield, Frank S. Hopkins, Edwin L. James, Charles Gilmore Maphis, William Emmet Moore, and John Sharp Williams.
Arrangement
The papers of the Institute contain two record group numbers (RG-2/4/1.891 and RG-2/4/1.892) and one manuscript classification number (2792-a), but all folders are interfiled with RG-2/4/1.891. Groups I-III consist of RG-2/4/1.891. Group IV consists entirely of RG-2/4/1.892. Group V consists of manuscript classification number 2792-a. Folders transferred from the Papers of the University Bursar (original manuscript classification number 8692-y) are interfiled into boxes 92 & 93. Also included in the collection are original manuscript collection numbers 1540-a, 1540-b. For more information, please see University Archives Control Folder RG-2/4.
Contents List
- Series I: Clippings (Box 1-16)
  - Baltimore Sun 1927 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous 1927 (Box 1)
  - New York Times 1927 (Box 1)
  - Publicity-Roanoke World News 1927 (Box 1)
  - Richmond Times Dispatch 1927 (Box 1)
  - Special Correspondents 1927 (Box 1)
  - Washington Post 1927 (Box 1)
  - Williamstown 1927 (Box 1)
  - Charlottesville, Va.-Daily Progress n.d. (Box 1)
  - Virginia Editorials 1928 (Box 1)
  - A-Q 1927, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - R-V 1928, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Michigan 1929 (Box 2)
  - Minnesota 1929 (Box 2)
  - Mississippi 1929 (Box 2)
  - Missouri 1929 (Box 2)
  - Montana 1929 (Box 2)
  - Nebraska 1929 (Box 2)
  - Nevada 1929 (Box 2)
  - New Hampshire 1929 (Box 2)
  - New Jersey 1929 (Box 2)
  - New Mexico 1929 (Box 2)
  - New York 1929 (Box 2)
  - New York City 1929 (Box 2)
  - Newspaper Clippings 1929 (Box 2)
  - North Carolina 1929 (Box 2)
  - North Dakota 1929 (Box 2)
  - Ohio 1929 (Box 2)
  - Oklahoma 1929 (Box 3)
  - Oregon 1929 (Box 3)
  - Pennsylvania 1929 (Box 3)
  - Rhode Island 1929 (Box 3)
  - South Carolina 1929 (Box 3)
  - South Dakota 1929 (Box 3)
  - Tennessee 1929 (Box 3)
  - Texas 1929 (Box 3)
  - Utah 1929 (Box 3)
  - Vermont 1929 (Box 3)
  - Virginia 1929 (Box 3)
  - Virginia-Editorials 1929 (Box 3)
  - Virginia-Lynchburg 1929 (Box 3)
  - Newport News & Norfolk 1929 (Box 3)
  - Virginia-Richmond 1929 (Box 3)
  - Virginia-Roanoke 1929 (Box 3)
  - Virginia-Staunton & Waynesboro 1929 (Box 3)
  - Washington 1929 (Box 3)
  - Washington, D.C. 1929 (Box 3)
  - Wisconsin 1929 (Box 3)
  - Wyoming 1929 (Box 3)
  - Clippings-Editorials 1929, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Alabama 1930 (Box 4)
  - Arizona 1930 (Box 4)
  - Arkansas 1930 (Box 4)
  - California 1930 (Box 4)
  - Colorado 1930 (Box 4)
  - Connecticut 1930 (Box 4)
  - Delaware 1930 (Box 4)
  - Florida 1930 (Box 4)
  - Georgia 1930 (Box 4)
  - Idaho 1930 (Box 4)
  - Illinois 1930 (Box 4)
  - Indiana 1930 (Box 4)
  - Iowa 1930 (Box 5)
  - Kansas 1930 (Box 5)
  - Kentucky 1930 (Box 5)
  - La Prensa 1930 (Box 5)
  - Louisiana 1930 (Box 5)
  - Maine 1930 (Box 5)
  - Maryland 1930 (Box 5)
  - Massachusetts 1930 (Box 5)
  - Michigan 1930 (Box 5)
  - Minnesota 1930 (Box 5)
  - Mississippi 1930 (Box 5)
  - Missouri 1930 (Box 5)
  - Montana 1930 (Box 5)
  - New York 1930 (Box 5)
  - Virginia-Editorials 1930 (Box 5)
  - Washington 1930 (Box 5)
  - Washington, D.C. 1930 (Box 5)
  - West Virginia 1930 (Box 5)
  - Wisconsin 1930 (Box 5)
  - Wyoming 1930 (Box 5)
  - Clippings-Editorials 1930, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - New Mexico 1931 (Box 6)
  - New York 1931 (Box 6)
  - North Carolina 1931 (Box 6)
  - North Dakota 1931 (Box 6)
  - Ohio 1931 (Box 6)
  - Oklahoma 1931 (Box 6)
  - Oregon 1931 (Box 6)
  - Pennsylvania 1931 (Box 6)
  - Rhode Island 1931 (Box 6)
  - South Carolina 1931 (Box 6)
  - South Dakota 1931 (Box 6)
  - Tennessee 1931 (Box 6)
  - Virginia 1931, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Alabama 1932 (Box 7)
  - Arkansas 1932 (Box 7)
  - California 1932 (Box 7)
  - Connecticut 1932 (Box 7)
  - Delaware 1932 (Box 7)
  - District of Columbia 1932 (Box 7)
  - Editorials 1932, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Florida 1932 (Box 7)
  - Georgia 1932 (Box 7)
  - Illinois 1932 (Box 7)
  - Indiana 1932 (Box 8)
  - Iowa 1932 (Box 8)
  - Kansas 1932 (Box 8)
  - Kentucky 1932 (Box 8)
  - Louisiana 1932 (Box 8)
  - Maine 1932 (Box 8)
  - Maryland 1932 (Box 8)
  - Ohio 1934 (Box 8)
  - Oklahoma 1934 (Box 8)
  - Oregon 1934 (Box 8)
  - Pennsylvania 1934 (Box 8)
  - Rhode Island 1934 (Box 8)
  - South Carolina 1934 (Box 8)
  - South Dakota 1934 (Box 8)
  - Tennessee 1934 (Box 8)
  - Texas 1934 (Box 8)
  - Utah 1934 (Box 8)
  - Vermont 1934 (Box 8)
  - Virginia 1934, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Washington 1934 (Box 8)
  - West Virginia 1934 (Box 8)
  - Wisconsin 1934 (Box 8)
  - Indiana 1935 (Box 8)
  - Iowa 1935 (Box 8)
  - Kansas 1935 (Box 9)
  - Kentucky 1935 (Box 9)
  - Latin America 1935 (Box 9)
  - Louisiana 1935 (Box 9)
  - Maine 1935 (Box 9)
  - Maryland 1935 (Box 9)
  - Massachusetts 1935 (Box 9)
  - Michigan 1935 (Box 9)
  - Minnesota 1935 (Box 9)
  - Alabama 1936 (Box 9)
  - Arizona 1936 (Box 9)
  - Arkansas 1936 (Box 9)
  - California 1936 (Box 9)
  - Connecticut 1936 (Box 9)
  - Delaware 1936 (Box 9)
  - Florida 1936 (Box 9)
  - Georgia 1936 (Box 9)
  - Idaho 1936 (Box 10)
  - Illinois 1936 (Box 10)
  - Indiana 1936 (Box 10)
  - Iowa 1936 (Box 10)
  - Kansas 1936 (Box 10)
  - Kentucky 1936 (Box 10)
  - Louisiana 1936 (Box 10)
  - Maine 1936 (Box 10)
  - Maryland 1936 (Box 10)
  - Massachusetts 1936 (Box 10)
  - Michigan 1936 (Box 10)
  - Minnesota 1936 (Box 10)
  - Mississippi 1936 (Box 10)
  - Missouri 1936 (Box 10)
  - Montana 1936 (Box 10)
  - Nebraska 1936 (Box 10)
  - New Hampshire 1936 (Box 10)
  - New Jersey 1936 (Box 10)
  - New Mexico 1936 (Box 10)
  - New York 1936 (Box 11)
  - New York City 1936, 2 folders (Box 11)
  - North Carolina 1936 (Box 11)
  - North Dakota 1936 (Box 11)
  - Ohio 1936 (Box 11)
  - Oklahoma 1936 (Box 12)
  - Oregon 1936 (Box 12)
  - Pennsylvania 1936 (Box 12)
  - Periodical 1936, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Rhode Island 1936 (Box 12)
  - South Carolina 1936 (Box 12)
  - South Dakota 1936 (Box 12)
  - Tennessee 1936 (Box 12)
  - Texas 1936 (Box 12)
  - Vermont 1936 (Box 12)
  - Virginia A-H 1936, Folder 1 of 2 (Box 12)
  - Virginia A-H 1936, Folder 2 of 2 (Box 13)
  - Virginia G-Ri 1936, 4 folders (Box 13)
  - Virginia Ro-Z 1936, Folder 1 of 2 (Box 13)
  - Virginia Ro-Z 1936, Folder 2 of 2 (Box 14)
  - Washington 1936 (Box 14)
  - Washington, D.C. 1936 (Box 14)
  - West Virginia 1936 (Box 14)
  - Wisconsin 1936 (Box 14)
  - Newspaper Clippings 1937 (Box 14)
  - Maryland 1938 (Box 14)
  - Pennsylvania 1938 (Box 14)
  - Philippines 1938 (Box 14)
  - Rhode Island 1938 (Box 14)
  - South Carolina 1938 (Box 14)
  - South Dakota 1938 (Box 14)
  - Tennessee 1938 (Box 14)
  - Texas 1938 (Box 14)
  - Utah 1938 (Box 14)
  - Vermont 1938 (Box 14)
  - Maryland 1940 (Box 14)
  - Massachusetts 1940 (Box 14)
  - Michigan 1940 (Box 14)
  - Minnesota 1940 (Box 15)
  - Mississippi 1940 (Box 15)
  - Missouri 1940 (Box 15)
  - Montana 1940 (Box 15)
  - Nebraska 1940 (Box 15)
  - Nevada 1940 (Box 15)
  - New Jersey 1940 (Box 15)
  - New Mexico 1940 (Box 15)
  - New York 1940 (Box 15)
  - North Carolina 1940 (Box 15)
  - North Dakota 1940 (Box 15)
  - Ohio 1940 (Box 15)
  - Oklahoma 1940 (Box 15)
  - Pennsylvania 1940 (Box 16)
  - Rhode Island 1940 (Box 16)
  - South Carolina 1940 (Box 16)
  - South Dakota 1940 (Box 16)
  - Tennessee 1940 (Box 16)
  - Texas 1940 (Box 16)
  - Utah 1940 (Box 16)
  - Virginia 1940, 3 folders (Box 16)
  - Newspaper Clippings 1940 (Box 16)
  - Newspaper Clippings 1941 (Box 16)
  - Newspaper Clippings 1953 (Box 16)
- Series II: Original Manuscripts-Round Table, Open Forum, Special Conference (Box 17-53)
  - Welcome; Evening, Morning Addresses
    - Address, Dr. Charles G. Maphis; Address, Hon. Harry Flood Byrd; "The Bringing of the Atlantic Ocean a Thousand Miles Inland," Henry J. Allen 1927 August 8 (Box 17)
    - "The Present Status of the League of Nations," Hon. John H. Clarke; "The Nation's Business," Gen. H.M. Lord 1927 August 9 (Box 17)
    - "Treasury Financing," Hon. Ogden L. Mills 1927 August 10 (Box 17)
    - "The Present Relation of the Government of the United States to the World Court of Justice," Hon. John H. Clarke 1927 August 11 (Box 17)
    - "The Relation of State Rights to the Industrialization of the South," Hon. Albert C. Ritchie; "Municipal Government and the Future of American Democracy," Hon. Albert C. Ritchie 1927 August 12 (Box 17)
    - "Private Rights and Public Authority," Hon. William Gibbs; Address, Maj. R. H. Ranger; "The Future of Aviation," Maj. Gen. Mason M. Patrick; "Imponderables of European Politics," Lindsay Rogers 1927 August 13 (Box 17)
    - "The Makers and the Making of the Constitution," Ralph R. Lounsbury; "Real and Imagined Dangers of the Constitution," Ralph R. Lounsbury 1927 August 15 (Box 17)
  - Evening Addresses
    - "Importance of Political Education," Daniel C. Roper; "The Relation of Education and Research and the Rural Problem," Dr. A. F. Wood 1927 August 17 (Box 17)
    - "Dictatorship or Democracy," Adamantios Th. Polyzoides; "The Eighteenth Amendment: Its Relation to the Constitution," Edward Dunford 1927 August 18 (Box 17)
    - "The 18th Amendment and the Volstead Act," Hon. William Cabell Bruce 1927 August [18] (Box 17)
    - "The Solid South: A National Problem," Henry W. Anderson 1927 August 19 (Box 17)
    - Addresses of Speakers 1928 (Box 17)
    - "Religion and Public Affairs," Dr. Joseph Fort Newton 1928 August 5 (Box 17)
    - "Awakening the Public Conscience to Proper City Management," George A. Levy; "Have We a Crisis of Democracy?," Count Carlo Sforza 1928 August 7 (Box 17)
    - "The Strong Man's Burden," Dr. William J. Hickson; "The South at the Turn of the Road," Dr. William E. Dodd; "Law and Aeronautics," Dr. Otto Schreiber 1928 August 9 (Box 17)
    - "Should the Eighteenth Amendment and All Laws Enacted Pursuant Thereto be Continued and Enforced?," John Philip Hill 1928 August 10 (Box 17)
    - Count Carlo Sforza 1928 August 11 (Box 17)
    - "Newspaper vs. Political Corruption," Boyd Gurley 1928 August 13 (Box 17)
    - Hon. John R. Davies 1928 August 15 (Box 17)
    - "Governmental Fundamentals," Hon. Finis J. Garrett 1928 August 16 (Box 17)
    - Address, Mrs. Nellie Tayloe Ross 1928 August 17 (Box 17)
  - Round Table: "The Agricultural Problem"
    - Program 1928 August (Box 17)
    - Report 1928 August 6-10, 3 folders (Box 17)
    - "Overproduction Not the Sum Total in Inequality of Prices," [Dole] 1928 August (Box 17)
    - "What Federal and State Aid Should Agriculture Receive?," Eric Englund 1928 August 8 (Box 17)
    - "Need for a Land Utilization Program," Elbert S. Brigham; Summary 1928 August 13 (Box 17)
    - "The Agricultural Problem in the Middle West," Hon. L. Jesse Dickinson; "Is There a Genuine Agricultural Problem?," Hon. Evans Woolen 1928 August 14 (Box 17)
    - "Changes in Southern Agriculture and the Problems Arising Therefrom," W. J. Spillman, Sr.; Summary 1928 August 15 (Box 17)
    - "The Agricultural Surplus Problem," W. J. Spillman, Sr.; Summary 1928 August 17 (Box 17)
  - Round Table: "Our Latin American Relations"
    - Program 1928 August (Box 18)
    - Preliminary Statement, Dr. John H. Latané 1928 August 6 (Box 18)
    - "Nationalistic Differentiation in Hispanic America," Hon. Federico A. Peyet 1928 August 7 (Box 18)
    - "Nicaragua," John Clayton; "Mexico," John Clayton 1928 August 13 (Box 18)
    - "Latin American Distrust--Its Causes," William T. Morrey 1928 August 15 (Box 18)
    - Summary 1928 August 5-18 (Box 18)
  - Round Table: "Municipal Management"
    - Program; Statement, Dr. Thomas H. Reed 1928 August (Box 18)
    - Address, Joseph T. Miller; "Personnel Selection," Fred Telford; Summary 1928 August 8 (Box 18)
    - Secretary's Report 1928 August 10 (Box 18)
    - Secretary's Summary 1928 August 18 (Box 18)
  - Round Table: "Political Parties and Electoral Problems"
    - Program 1928 August (Box 18)
    - Summary 1928 August 6 (Box 18)
    - Mrs. Emily Newell Blair - Don C. Seitz 1928 August 8 (Box 18)
    - Report 1928 August (Box 18)
    - Summary 1928 August 8-17, 5 folders (Box 18)
    - [Arbitration of Commercial Disputes] 1928 August (Box 18)
    - "Trade Associations and Commercial Arbitration," Daniel Bloomfield 1928 August 17 (Box 18)
  - Round Table: "Women in Modern Society"
    - Program 1928 August (Box 18)
    - "Women in Modern Society," Aurelia H. Reinhardt 1928 August 7 (Box 18)
    - "Women in Education," Charl Ormond Williams 1928 August 9 (Box 18)
  - Round Table: "County and Township Government"
    - Program 1928 August (Box 18)
    - Summary 1928 August 7 (Box 18)
    - Report 1928 August 9 (Box 18)
    - [County and Township Government], Alden C. Fensel; Summary 1928 August 11 (Box 18)
    - Summary 1928 August 14 (Box 18)
    - Summary 1928 August 16 (Box 18)
  - Round Table: "The Tax Problem"
    - Program 1928 August (Box 18)
  - Round Table: "The Influence of the Press in Public Affairs"
    - Program 1928 August (Box 18)
    - Address, Willis J. Abbot 1928 August 14 (Box 18)
    - Report 1928 August 9-18, 5 folders (Box 18)
  - Round Table: "The Economic and Industrial Development of the South"
    - Program; "The Solid South" 1928 August (Box 18)
    - "The Economic and Industrial Progress of the South," Richard H. Edmonds 1928 August 7 (Box 18)
    - "What Can Advertising Do for the South?," Charles Pelham 1928 August 8 (Box 18)
    - "The Economic and Industrial Development of the South," W. Gerald Holmes 1928 August 9 (Box 18)
    - William D. Ennis (empty); Address, Dr. Philip O. Wells 1928 August 14 (Box 18)
    - "Power and Matter," Victor S. Clark 1928 August 16 (Box 18)
    - Report 1928 August 7-9, 2 folders (Box 18)
    - Summary 1928 August 11-16, 3 folders (Box 18)
  - Open Forum
    - "Regional Government," Dr. Thomas H. Reed 1928 August 8 (Box 18)
    - "Our Nation's Obligation to Its Schools," Miss Charl Ormond Williams 1928 August 9 (Box 18)
    - Address, Mrs. W. L. Lawton; "Law, Manners, and Outdoor Advertising," J. W. Digges; "The Cooperative Trend of Industry," Mrs. Harry Lilly 1928 August 11 (Box 18)
    - "The Economic and Industrial Development of the South," Bradford Knapp 1928 August 13 (Box 18)
  - Round Table: "The Country Church and Public Affairs"
    - "The Introduction," Henry W. McLaughlin; "Preface" 1929 August (Box 18)
  - Evening Addresses
    - Vesper Service, "Religion and Public Affairs," Dr. Walter Russell Bowie 1929 August 4 (Box 18)
    - "Welcome on Behalf of the Institute," Dr. Charles G. Maphis; "Welcome on Behalf of the State," Hon. John R. Saunders; "Legislative Farm Relief," Hon. Carter Glass 1929 August 5 (Box 18)
    - "A Realistic Approach to the Problems of Democracy," Norman Thomas; "The Passing of the Old United States," Dr. William E. Dodd 1929 August 7 (Box 18)
    - "The Rural Church and the Country Newspaper," Hon. James J. Finney; "Twenty Years with Country Churches," Warren H. Wilson 1929 August 8 (Box 18)
    - "Farm Relief," Hon. Tom Connally; "The Farmer and the Sheriff," Hon. David J. Walsh 1929 August 9 (Box 18)
    - "Government's Responsibility for Disrespect of the Law," W. W. Coxe 1929 August 10 (Box 18)
    - "The Growth of Chemical Industry in the South," H.C. Parmelee 1929 August 10 (Box 19)
    - "Who, What was Christ?," Dr. William Evans 1929 August 11 (Box 19)
    - "American Electoral Mission in Nicaragua," Gen. Frank R. McCoy 1929 (Box 19)
    - "The Newspaper and the Modern Age," Sherwood Anderson 1929 August 12 (Box 19)
    - "The Dilemma of Intervention," Dr. Henry Kittredge Norton 1929 August 13 (Box 19)
    - "The Enforcement of the 18th Amendment and the Volstead Act from the Point of View of the Individual States," His Excellency Albert C. Ritchie; "Prohibition," Stanley High 1929 August 14 (Box 19)
  - Round Table: "Democracy as Operative in America"
    - "Nationality," Dr. Emma Wold 1929 August 5 (Box 19)
    - "The Growth of Federal Power," Douglas Arant 1929 August 7 (Box 19)
    - "Democracy and Administration," C.E. Righter 1929 August 12 (Box 19)
    - "Alternatives to Democracy: Monarchy," Dr. W. J. Shepard; "Alternatives to Democracy," Prof. Pitman B. Potter 1929 August 14 (Box 19)
    - "Problems of Democracy Abroad," Adamantios Th. Polyzoides 1929 August 16 (Box 19)
  - Round Table: "Our Latin American Relations"
    - "American News Service in Latin-America," J. H. Furay; "The Importance of Inter American Press Relations," Jacinto Lopez; "Unofficial Cultural Interchanges Between the Americas," Muma Lee (Mrs. Luíz Munoz Marín) 1929 August 5 (Box 19)
    - "Why Does Latin-America Fear Increasing Investment of United States Capital?," Dr. Clarence H. Haring; "Difficulties and Dangers Involved in the Increased Investment of American Capital in Latin- America," Dr. Victor Belaúnde; "The Present Economic Policy of the United States in Latin-America and Its Effect on Private American Investments," Hon. Sumner Welles 1929 August 7 (Box 19)
    - "Pan American Treaties for Conciliation and Arbitration," Dr. Ricardo J. Alfaro; "The Good Faith of the United States," Carlos Eduardo Castaneda; "Dangers of Our Present Policy," W. P. Maddox 1929 August 9 (Box 19)
    - "Porto [Puerto] Rico and the Sugar Tariff," Dr. Thomas E. Benner; "Tariffs and Neighbors," Dr. Henry Kittredge Norton; "Tariff as Trade Barriers," Hon. Alfred Pearce Dennis; Summary 1929 August 12 (Box 19)
    - "The Mexican Agrarian Revolution," Dr. Frank Tannenbaum; "Mexico's Dilemma," Carlos Eduardo Castaneda; "Twenty Years of Mexican Revolution," Dr. Ernest Gruening; "The Religious Settlement in Mexico," Patrick J. Ward; "American Neutrality and the League of Nations," Prof. Earl Crecraft 1929 August 14 (Box 19)
    - "American Policy in Central America and the Caribbean Region," Hon. Dana Munro; "The True Nature of American Political Relations with Central-America and the Caribbean States," Dr. T. Seydel Vaca; "The United States and International Justice," Dr. Camilo Barcia Trelles 1929 August 16 (Box 19)
    - Report 1929 (Box 19)
    - Summary 1929 (Box 19)
    - Informal Discussion 1929 August 16 (Box 19)
    - Report 1929 (Box 19)
    - Open Discussion 1929 August 5-9, 7 folders (Box 19)
  - Open Forum
    - "Does the Policy of the Department of State of Refusing to Recognize Governments Set Up by Force Work to the Best Advantage of the United States and of the Latin-American Countries Concerned?," Dr. Clarence Haring 1929 August 8 (Box 19)
  - Round Table: "The Press in Public Affairs"
    - "The Newspaper as a Factor in Municipal Affairs," Harold S. Buttheim 1929 August 9 (Box 20)
    - "The American Newspaper in Foreign Affairs," Adamantios Th. Polyzoides 1929 August 17 (Box 20)
  - Round Table: "Law Enforcement"
    - "Observations on the Survey of Organized Crime in Chicago," John Landesco 1929 August 6 (Box 20)
    - "The Prison as a Crime-Breeder," Dr. Hastings H. Hart 1929 August 8 (Box 20)
    - "Criminal Justice in Virginia," Prof. Hugh N. Fuller; "Crime from a Social Standpoint," Frank Bane 1929 August 10 (Box 20)
    - "Federal Prohibition Law Enforcement," Hon. James M. Doran; "Effect of General Prohibition on General Problems of Law Enforcement," Arthur V. Lashley; "Law Enforcement," William B. Swaney 1929 August 15 (Box 20)
  - Round Table: "Problems of Contemporary Politics"
    - Report 1929 August 8-10 (Box 20)
  - Open Forum
    - "Labor Situation in the South," Bruce Crawford 1929 August 5 (Box 20)
    - "Southern Labor Problems," Tom Trippett 1929 August 6 (Box 20)
    - "The Country Life of the Nation," Hon. B. F. Yoakum 1929 August 9 (Box 20)
    - "The Newspaper and Public Affairs," Louis I. Jaffe 1929 August 10 (Box 20)
    - "Government and Business," Edward N. Hurley 1929 August 12 (Box 20)
    - "Democracy as Operative in America," [Dr. Reed or Prof. John A. Fairlie] 1929 August 14 (Box 20)
    - "Does the 18th Amendment Confer the Same Power Upon the Several States to Enforce Its Provisions that It Confers Upon Congress, and Are They Under Equal Obligation to Assume the burden of Enforcement?," James J Britt; "My Recollection of the Revolution," Dr. Paul Barringer 1929 August 15 (Box 20)
    - Debate: "Resolve That the Deep Waterway Connecting the Great Lakes with the Atlantic Ocean shall be by the St. Lawrence River Rather than by the New York State Route and Hudson River," Mr. Edward C. Carrington and Hon. W. L. Harding 1929 August 16 (Box 20)
  - Evening Addresses
    - "Put the Liquor Problem Up to the People," Hon. Wade H. Ellis 1929 August 15 (Box 20)